Guide to the Jack Underhill papers, 1963-1997
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Jack Underhill papers
1963-1997
C0134
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
28.25 Linear feet (72 boxes)
The Underhill papers include reports, correspondence, financial documents, plans, publications, and general information on new planned communities. Also included is a series of oversized maps from different new towns including Flower Mound, St. Charles and Roosevelt Island. The collection is comprised of Jack Underhill's personal papers that he accumulated while employed with the Department of Housing and Urban Development. The papers document the Federal New Communities Program which sponsored the development of 13 new towns. It also documents Underhill's research interests in private new towns and international urban planning. The collection covers the period of time from the 1963 to 1997.
Jack Underhill
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Jack Underhill in in October of 1997 and December of 1998. Series 5 was donated in 2011.
Biographical Information
Jack Underhill retired in 1997 after 42 years of Federal service, 33 years of which were at Department of Housing and Urban Development. He served as a research analyst for the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). The department was created in 1937 under the U.S. Housing Act of 1937 and was later becomes a cabinet-level agency in 1965. HUD's mission is to increase home ownership, support community development, and increase access to affordable housing free from discrimination.
He has written books on Soviet and French New Towns and edited two joint publications with the Soviets on new towns. He holds a Masters in Public Administration Harvard University and a PhD in Public Policy from George Mason University. Since retirement, he has worked as a consultant, served as chairman of the board of trustees for the Annandale United Methodist Church, and served as treasurer of the Virginia Poet's Society and the Planning for Peace Foundation.
Scope and Content
The Underhill papers include reports, correspondence, financial documents, plans, publications, and general information on new planned communities. Also included is a series of oversized maps from different new towns including Flower Mound, St. Charles and Roosevelt Island. The collection is comprised of Jack Underhill's personal papers that he accumulated while employed with the Department of Housing and Urban Development. The papers document the Federal New Communities Program which sponsored the development of 13 new towns. It also documents Underhill's research interests in private new towns and international urban planning. The collection covers the period of time from the 1963 to 1997.
Series 1 is correspondence which is dated from 1970 to 1983. The correspondence is primarily related to New Community Development Corporation. The correspondence is also broken down into months and years that they were received.
Series 2 is compiled of reports that are dated from 1967 to 1990. The information on the reports is about different planned communities in progress. Some of the reports in this series were submitted to Congress. Also included in the series are two boxes of microfiche.
Series 3 is plans involving various planned community projects that dates from 1969 to 1992. The information in the series includes project summaries, project evaluations, business plans and project lists.
Series 4 includes information on different places that is dated from 1968 to 1985. The information is on a variety of places within the United States. Also in the series are reports on places outside the United States, such as Russia, France and Israel. The information from the foreign countries are evaluations on the planned communities in those countries. The last few boxes in this series are not just paper work instead it is census data and computer printouts from the different planned communities.
Series 5 contains information dated from 1970-1997. This series contains documents on welfare reform, homelessness, and housing and climate in the United States and the former Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. There are also reports, assessments, and summaries.
Series 6 is a variety of histories dated from 1964 to 1983. The paperwork includes the history of Reston, administration history of different project and new planned communities.
Series 7 includes financial information that is dated from 1969 to 1983. The documents include information on the budget, costs, mortgages and banking for the different planned communities that were being built and maintained during that time period.
Series 8 is general information from 1963 to 1987. The documents in the series from a variety of different sources, including reference material, outlines, fact sheets, American Institution of Architects nc Conference, interviews, New League Community and New Town.
Series 9 is a variety of publications that were published from 1965 to 1983. The items that are included in this series are different articles, journals and press releases.
Series 10 are drafts from different books that are dated from 1969 to 1984. The books are drafts, work books and briefing books for different witnesses that are testifying before Congress.
Series 11 is a collection of oversized maps. The New Town maps document different locations that are included in the paperwork in the rest of the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into 11 Series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1970-1983 (Boxes 1-8)
Series 2: Reports, 1967-1990 (Boxes 8-18)
Series 3: Plans, 1969-1992 (Boxes 19-25)
Series 4: Places, 1968-1985 (Boxes 25-37)
Series 5: Housing and Urban Development, 1970-1997 (Boxes 63-72)
Series 6: Histories, 1964-1983 (Boxes 38-40)
Series 7: Finance, 1969-1983 (Boxes 40-43)
Series 8: General Information, 1963-1987 (Boxes 44-52)
Series 9: Publications, 1965-1983 (Boxes 52-55)
Series 10: Books, 1969-1984 (Boxes 55-60)
Series 11: Oversize, 1980 (Mapcase)
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other papers on the development of new towns, particularly Reston, Virginia. Also of related interest are the papers of David Pass papers.
Index Terms
Persons:
Underhill, Jack A.
Corporate Names:
United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.
Subjects:
Housing.; Planned communities.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1970-1983; (7.5 boxes)
  The majority of the correspondences in this series are about the New Community Development Corporation Program. The series has 55 folders in 8 boxes.
  - New Community Program Founding of Program, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    483.6
    - Article: Charles M. Harr, The Mortgage Banker, "New Financing for Planned Communities", September 1969; 1.
    - Memo: Paul Brace to Arthur A. Davis, "HUD Financed Research Projects Related to New Communities", March 27, 1969; 2.
    - Memo: Paul Brace to Robert M. Paul, "FY 69 Research Program", March 18, 1969; 3.
    - Memo: Victor J. Pettit to John A. Bell, "Proposal for Combining New Community Obligations", November 21, 1969; 4.
    - Note: John A. Bell to Hilbert Ferrerman, Irving P. Margulies, Ivan S. Meitus, November 5, 1969; 5.
    - Note: John A. Bell to Sherman Unger, "Issues Involved in Clearance of Title IV Regulations For Federal Register Publications Under A Notice of Proposed Rulemaking", November 22, 1969; 6.
    - Note: William Rutzick to Grant Mitchell, "Title VII Assistance to Existing New Communities", May 5, 1971; 7.
    - Paper: Anonymous, "Chronological History of The New Communities Act of 1968", no date; 8.
    - Paper: U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development New Communities Division, "Survey and Analysis of Large Developments and New Communities Completed and Under Construction in the United States Since 1947", February 1969; 9.
  - New Communities-Financial Aspects, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    484.9
    - Press Release: Department of Housing and Urban Development, "HUD Board Takes Action on Two New Communities", June 28, 1979; 1.
    - Report: New Community Development Corporation, "1978 Annual Report - New Community Development Corporation", January 10, 1979; 2.
    - Certification and Acceptance: Department of Housing and Urban Development, "Certification and Acceptance: Woodlands Development Corporation", September 6, 1972; 3.
  - New Communities Program-Legal Aspects, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    484.8
    - Letter: Radcliffe Park to S. Leigh Curry, Jr., October 16, 1970; 1.
  - Lilley, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    80.1
  - Urban Policy Announcements, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    484.17
    - Paper: Samuel C. Jackson, "A New Generation of New Communities", November 3-6, 1971; 1.
  - Urban Policy Announcement, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    484.15
    - Memo: William J. Nicoson to Samuel C. Jackson, "New Communities Initiatives", December 30, 1971; 1.
    - Note: James Moynihan to Frederick A. Mclaughlin, "Role of N.T. in Relieving the Ghetto Problem", October 5, 1967; 2.
    - Paper: Jack Underhill, "Proposal for Strengthening the Role of New Communities in Implementing National Urban Growth Strategy", October 27, 1971; 3.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Recommendations Concerning New Communities and National Urban Growth Policy", no date; 4.
  - Urban Policy Announcements, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    484.16
    - Memo: William J. Nicoson to Samuel C. Jackson, "Proposed State Legislation for FY 1973", February 11, 1972; 1.
    - Paper: Anonymous, "Discussion Paper for Outline on National Community Development Bank", no date; 2.
    - Press Release: American Institute of Architects, "Strategy for Builging a Better America Unveiled by AIA", January 24, 1972; 3.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Highlights of the 'Housing and Urban Development Act of 1974' as approved by the Subcommitte on Housing April 30, 1974", May 2, 1974; 4.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Summary of Initiatives to Strengthen The New Communities Programs", no date; 5.
    - Report: William J. Nicoson, "Attachment A: Detailed Justification for Legislative Proposals", no date; 6.
  - Better Communities Credit Assistance Act, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    80.8
  - Discussion and Highlights, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    484.13
    - Paper: New Community Development Corporation, "Urban New Towns: A Title VII Incentive of New-Towns-In-Towns", August 29, 1980; 1.
    - Paper: R. E. Engelen and D. G. Stuart, "The Potential for New-Towns In-Town: American Experience in Two Cities", July 1979; 2.
    - Paper: Rodney E. Engelen, "Making New Towns - In Town Work", July 1975; 3.
    - Report: Jack Underhill, "Proposed Up-Date on New-Town-In-Town Study", June 19, 1978; 4.
    - Report: Anonymous, "New-Towns-In-Towns: Their Potential and Problems", no date; 5.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Analyzing the Market for a New-Town-in-Town", July 1978; 6.
  - Discussion and Highlights, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    484.14
    - Memo: John B. Clinton to William White, "Potential NTIT Projects", May 3, 1977; 1.
    - Paper: Joseph T. Bill, "New-Towns-In-Town A Paper Containing: Background, Definition, Discussion, Financing, MXD Relationship and Federal Role", October 1979; 2.
  - Otto Stolz, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    483.14
    - Letter: John Freeman to Otto Stolz, "Background Paper on New Communities Past, Present, and Future", November 12, 1974; 1.
  - Evaluation [empty]and Evaluation no.2, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    80.11
  - Correspondence, January-June, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    126.1
  - Correspondence, July-December, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    126.2
  - Housing and Urband Development Board of Directors, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    483.15
    - Note: Grant E. Mitchell to Robert Elliot, August 23, 1974; 1.
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    126.3
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    126.4
  - Correspondence, January-May, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    126.5
  - Johnathan Correspondence from Resident's Association to Housing and Urban Development, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    117.6
  - Correspondence, June-December, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    126.6
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    127.1
  - Correspondence, May-December, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    127.2
  - Legislation Curzan, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    488.10
  - Antecendents to Study-History Title VII Projects, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    83.1
  - Freedom of Information, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    81.10
  - New Community Development Corporation Program Correspondence Files-Calendar Year, January, 1978-May, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    124.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Program Correspondence Files-Calendar Year, June, 1978-November, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    124.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Program Correspondence Files-Calendar Year, December, 1978-May, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    124.6
  - Private New Towns, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    83.3
  - Correspondence, Minutes and Financial Data, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    144.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Program Correspondence Files-Calendar Year, June, 1978-December, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    125.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 1-69 [1-24], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    132.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 1-69 [28-47], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    132.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 1-69 [48-69], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    132.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 70-133 [71-94], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    132.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 70-133 [95-133], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    132.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 136-199 [136-154], 1970s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    133.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 136-199 [155-180], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 1)
    133.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 136-199 [181-199], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    133.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 200-250 [200-250], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    133.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 200-275 [251-275], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    133.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 200-290 [276-290], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    133.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 291-340 [291-319] (Section III), 1970s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    133.7
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 291-340 [320-332] (Section III), 1970s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    134.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 291-340 [333-340], 1970s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    134.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 341-396 [341-368] (Section IV), 1970s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    134.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 341-396 [369-396], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 2)
    134.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 397-447 [397-411], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    134.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 397-447 [412-431], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    134.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 397-447 [432-447], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    135.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 448-493 [448-473], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 6)
    135.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 448-493 [4474-486], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 7)
    135.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 448-493 [487-493], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 8)
    135.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 495-496, 1026 and unmarked, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    135.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2007-2172 [unmarked], 1970s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    135.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2007-2172 [2007-2124], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    135.7
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2007-2172 [2125-2135], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    135.8
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2007-2172 [2136-2172], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 3)
    136.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2178-2270 [2178-2205], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    136.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2178-2270 [2206-2221], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 5)
    136.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2178-2270 [2222-2250], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 6)
    136.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2178-2270 [2251-2270], 1970s (Box 7, Folder 7)
    136.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [Riverton Report by Department of Housing and Urban Development], 1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    137.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2251-2301 [2251-2301], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 1)
    137.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [2302-2331], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 2)
    137.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [2332-2360], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 3)
    137.4
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [2361-2394], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 4)
    137.5
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [2395-2484], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 5)
    137.6
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2271-2500 [2485-2500], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 6)
    138.1
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2501-2548 [2501-2548], 1970s (Box 8, Folder 7)
    138.2
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2549-2585 [2549-2585], 1970s (Box 9, Folder 1)
    138.3
  - New Community Development Corporation Correspondence, Reports 2549-2585 [unmarked], 1970s (Box 9, Folder 2)
    138.4
- Series 2: Reports, 1967-1990; (10.5 boxes)
  This series are reports submitted about the different planned communities in progress. The series has 87 folders in 9 boxes plus the two boxes of microfiche
  - Urban America: Goals and Problems-Subcommittee on Urban Affairs (90th Congress), 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    106.6
  - Urban America: Goals and Problems Hearings before Subcommittee on Urban Affairs (90th Congress), 1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    106.7
  - Summary Report on New Towns, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    97.9
  - New Towns Task Force, October 16, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    483.9
    - Report: Task Force on New Towns, "Supplemental Information", November 4, 1967; 1.
  - New Towns Task Force Report, October 16, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    483.8
    - Report: Task Force on New Towns, "Summary Report of the Task Force on New Towns", October 16, 1967; 1.
  - New Towns Task Force, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    483.7
    - Memo: Charles M. Haar to Joseph A. Califano, Jr. "Report of the Taskforce on New Towns", October 16, 1967; 1.
    - Report: David Scribner and Associates, Inc., "A New Communities Guide Line Study", November 1, 1968; 2.
  - New Communities Act, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    484.19
    - Report: Anonymous, "Federal Aid for New Communities", August 1968; 1.
    - Report: M. B. Zuckerman, "Zurban Report", ca. 1966; 2.
  - Fort Lincoln New Town Report, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    113.6
  - Minority Business Opportunities report by Small Bussiness Administration, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    105.8
  - Urbank, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    80.12
  - Legislation Javits Bill 3025, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    127.3
  - Fort Lincoln New Town Final Planning Report, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    97.5
  - Density, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    100.6
  - Cedar Riverside Properties Report on Audit, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    109.3
  - Legislation Domestic Growth Act, etc., 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    127.4
  - Maumelle Report, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    99.7
  - St. Charles Report, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    99.8
  - Environmental Quality-1st Annual report of Council on Environmental Quality, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    106.8
  - U.S. Senate Committee Testimony on Residential Segregation, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    112.4
  - Cedar Riverside Properties-Certified Public Accountant Report, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    109.4
  - Housing New Communities-Tables, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    484.7
    - Table: Department of Housing and Urban Development, "Basic Data on Selected New Community Proposals which were Never Approved, Key Dates and Final Disposition", no date; 1.
  - Research Report on Irvine Community Association, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    112.6
  - Sparkman [Congressional Record], 1971 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    127.6
  - Reports/Forms-Internal New Communities Administration, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    129.2
  - Reports/Forms-Internal New Communities Administration, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    129.1
  - Cedar Riverside Land Company Revised Report on Audit, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    109.2
  - Executive Summary, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    484.4
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Flower Mound New Town", November 1973; 1.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Interstate Land Development Company, Inc., St. Charles Communities", October 1973; 2.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Jonathan", November 4, 1973; 3.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Maumelle New Town", November 24, 1973; 4.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Park Forest South", November 4, 1973; 5.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Riverton", November 4, 1973; 6.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Roosevelt Island", November 12, 1973; 7.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: St. Charles Communities", October 1973; 8.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Cedar Riverside", ca. 1973; 9.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Gananda", November 4, 1973; 10.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Harbison", November 4, 1973; 11.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Lysander", November 4, 1973; 12.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: San Antonio Ranch New Town", November 4, 1973; 13.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: Soul City", November 4, 1973; 14.
    - Report: Anonymous, "Executive Summary: The Woodlands", November 4, 1973; 15.
    - Report: Interstate Land Development Company, Inc., "Addendum to Executive Summary", October 23, 1973; 16.
  - Fort Lincoln New Town-DC Government Report, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    113.7
  - Fort Lincoln New Town-DC Government Report, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    113.8
  - Humphrey, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    80.4
  - National Association of Homebuilders, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    80.7
  - Columbia, Maryland Report, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    86.4
  - Newfields New Community Report, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    117.2
  - United Nations Inter-Regional Seminar on New Towns, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    98.8
  - Legislation League of New Community, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    80.5
  - Hartke, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    80.6
  - Getting the New Communities Program STarted: Progress and Problems, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    513.1
  - Rockefeller Bank, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    482.3
  - Cedar Riverside Properties-Reports on Audit Procedures, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    109.1
  - Newfields, Dayton, Ohio, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    86.3
  - Granada-Summary, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    86.16
  - University Community Properties Incorporated-Report on Audit Procedures, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    118.6
  - Report on the New Communities Program, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    129.6